all right
[Music]
what is the impact of chewing gum on bad
breath in the Journal of evidence-based
dental practice a study compared the
levels of stinky breath compounds in
people's mouths before and after chewing
mint gum for 15 minutes and they found
that chewing gum significantly decreased
the levels of all the volatile silver
compounds they tested reducing them all
by about half which they attribute to
the effect that chewing gum has on
salivation how do we know that the mint
didn't have anything to do with it
because flavorless chewing gum base
without any active ingredient can work
too so chewing gum May indeed control
bad breath temporarily because it
triggers the salivary flow
that's thought to be why we wake up with
morning breath but it just goes away on
its own even if you don't brush your
teeth or anything here's the levels of
the stinky volatile sulfur compounds in
people's breath right when they wake up
dropping even before they eat breakfast
that's because we have one and a half
liters that's like six cups of saliva
bathing down our tongue daily but the
spigot is turned down at night and
bacteria grow in the stagnant puddle
that is your nighttime mouth
saliva works because of the simple fact
that larger saliva volumes allow
increased amounts of volatile sulfur
compounds to enter solution instead of
off-gassing the gases dissolve in the
fluid this can also be accomplished by
just drinking some water or by using
chewing gum since that causes your mouth
to water is there any flavor we can add
that makes it work better
a study on eucalyptus flavored chewing
gum was published people were randomized
due to a high concentration eucalyptus
gum five times a day a low concentration
gum or just flavorless gum and both of
the eucalyptus flavored gums
significantly beat out the control group
gum both quantitatively and
qualitatively
okay but where are you gonna find
eucalyptus gum what about the effect of
cinnamon
against one bad breath Associated
bacteria cinnamon oil kick tush
suggesting it's a promising substance to
incorporate into oral hygiene products
for controlling bad breath but it
utterly failed to control four other
types of bad breath bacteria these
studies were all just done in Petri
dishes though you don't really know if
cinnamon flavored gum would help with
bad breath until
you put it to the test the short-term
germ killing effect of sugar sweetened
cinnamon chewing gum on bacteria
associated with bad breath and the
researchers include that commercially
available sugar sweet and cinnamon
chewing gum May indeed benefit bad
breath but if you look at the actual
data the same gum without cinnamon oil
did no different than the gum with
cinnamon oil why were they so eager to
spin the results to suggest some sort of
unique benefit perhaps because this
study was funded by Wrigley
bottom line gum chewing per se is
considered to be helpful in reducing bad
breath by stimulating saliva flow and
mechanical cleansing even if there's no
quote unquote active ingredients in it
[Music]